{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "In Tamil Nadu, the movement started with __________ and __________",
            "optionA": "  The Saiva Nayanars ",
            "optionB": "  The Vaisnava Alvars ",
            "optionC": "  Nirguna Saints ",
            "optionD": "  Both A & B ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Tamil Nadu, the movement was started by Vaishnava saints {Alvars} and Shaiva saints {Nayanars}. The Alvars emphasized on Bhakti and gave reference to Bhagvata Puranas often, they were called the pioneers of Bhakti Movement. The same is applicable to the Saiva Nayanar poets. ",
            "keyString": "229427s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote a commentary on the Brahma sutras refuted Shari Kara and offered an interpretation based on the theistic ideas?",
            "optionA": "  Nimbarka ",
            "optionB": "  Ramanuja ",
            "optionC": "  Madhva ",
            "optionD": "  Vallabhacharya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamanuja gave a philosophic basis to the teachings of Vaishnavism. He wrote a commentary on the Brahma sutras, refuted Shari Kara and offered his own interpretation based on the theistic ideas. His commentaries on Brahma sutras are popularly known as Sri Bhasya. ",
            "keyString": "267878s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is an intensely emotional form of Hinduism that flourished from the sixteenth century, mainly in Bengal and eastern Orissa?",
            "optionA": "  Gaudiya Sampradaya ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna cult of Vallabhacharya ",
            "optionC": "  Shiva cult of Vallabhacharya ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Gaudiya Sampradaya is an intensely emotional form of Hinduism which flourished from the sixteenth century, mainly in Bengal and eastern Orissa. ",
            "keyString": "268125s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Bhakti Saints venerated in Sikhism, as well as Hindu warrior-ascetic traditions such as the Dadupanthis and the Niranjani Sampraday that emerged in north India during the Islamic rule?",
            "optionA": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionB": "  Eknath ",
            "optionC": "  Mirabai ",
            "optionD": "  Namdeva ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNamdev was influenced by Vaishnavism and became widely known in India for his devotional songs set to music (bhajan-kirtans). His philosophy contains both nirguna and saguna Brahman elements, with monistic themes. Namdev's legacy is remembered in modern times in the Varkari tradition, along with those of other gurus, with masses of people walking together in biannual pilgrimages to Pandharpur in south Maharashtra. He is also recognised in the North Indian traditions of the Dadu Panthis, Kabir Panthis and Sikhs. ",
            "keyString": "268270s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following propagated Dvaita or dualism of Jivatma and Pramatma in Kannada region?",
            "optionA": "  Mirabai ",
            "optionB": "  Nimbarka ",
            "optionC": "  Vallabhacharya ",
            "optionD": "  Madhav ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadhav propagated Dvaita or dualism of Jivatma and Paramatma. According to his philosophy, the world is not an illusion but a reality. God, soul, matter are unique in nature. ",
            "keyString": "268378s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following sect is emphasised on nirguni Bhakti - devotion to a divine without Gunas (qualities or form), but it accepts both nirguni and saguni forms of the divine?",
            "optionA": "  Sikhism ",
            "optionB": "  Shaivism ",
            "optionC": "  Vaishanvism ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Sikhism, \"nirguni Bhakti\" is emphasised \u2013 devotion to a divine without Gunas (qualities or form), but it accepts both nirguni and saguni forms of the divine. Guru Nanak, the first Sikh Guru and the founder of Sikhism, was a Bhakti saint. ",
            "keyString": "268482s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is not correct about Andal?",
            "optionA": "  Andal was a woman Alvar, the most striking features of her compositions were widely sung (and continue to be sung to date) ",
            "optionB": "  Andal was a woman Nayanar, she incorporated the prevailing caste system in the society ",
            "optionC": "  Andal saw herself as the beloved of Vishnu; her verses express her love for the deity ",
            "optionD": "  Andal saw herself as the beloved of Krishna; her verses express her love for the deity ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAndal was a woman Alvar, the most striking features of her compositions were widely sung (and continue to be sung to date), Andal saw herself as the beloved of Vishnu and Krishna; her verses express her love for the deity,",
            "keyString": "322659s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the Bhakti Movement?\nI. Originated as a reaction against caste division, untouchability and ritualism in India.\nII. Devotion was the pivotal point in the Bhakti cult in uniting human soul with god.",
            "optionA": "  I only ",
            "optionB": "  II only ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bhakti movement originated as a reaction against caste division, untouchability and ritualism in India. Devotion was the pivotal point in the Bhakti cult in uniting human soul with god. The basic concepts of the Bhakti cult though present in the Vedas, the Gita and Vishnupuran were not practiced by the masses until the appearances of Vaishnava Alwar and Shaiva Nayanar saints of South India in the seventh and twelfth centuries. ",
            "keyString": "323328s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was born into a Rathore royal family of Kudki district of Pali, Rajasthan and was a 16th-century Hindu mystic poet and devotee of Krishna?",
            "optionA": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionB": "  Mirabai ",
            "optionC": "  Tukaram ",
            "optionD": "  Kabir ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMirabai was a great Bhakti saint, Hindu mystic poet and a devotee of the Lord Krishna. Born in the late fifteenth century into a royal family of Rajasthan, Mira, from her childhood was a great devotee of Lord Krishna and wrote many beautiful poems in praise of her Lord. ",
            "keyString": "323739s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the impact of Bhakti Movement?\nI. Bhakti Movement resulted in a surge in Hindu literature in regional / vernacular languages mainly in the form of devotional poems and music.\nII. Bhakti Movement resulted in a surge in Buddhist text in regional / vernacular languages mainly in the form of devotional poems and music.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhakti Movement resulted in a surge in Hindu literature in regional / vernacular languages mainly in the form of devotional poems and music. II. Bhakti Movement resulted in a surge in Buddhist text in regional / vernacular languages mainly in the form of devotional poems and music. ",
            "keyString": "323902s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the features of Bhakti Movement?\nI. Condemnation of rituals, ceremonies and blind faith.\nII. Rejection of idol worship by many saints.",
            "optionA": "  I only ",
            "optionB": "  II only ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe features of Bhakti Movement are Condemnation of rituals, ceremonies and blind faith and Rejection of idol worship by many saints. ",
            "keyString": "324060s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which statement is not the advocacy of Nirguna Saints?",
            "optionA": "  It advocated the worshiped the anthropomorphic manifestations of the divine being, particularly Rama and Krishna ",
            "optionB": "  It is the concept of a formless God, which has no attributes or quality ",
            "optionC": "  It conceived as Ishvara, the personal and purely spiritual aspect of godhead, beyond all names and forms (nama-rupa), and is to be apprehended only by inner (mystical) experience ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNirguna Saints does not advocated the worshiped the anthropomorphic manifestations of the divine being, particularly Rama and Krishna. ",
            "keyString": "376278s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who began the Achintayabhedabhedavada School of theology?",
            "optionA": "  Chaitanya ",
            "optionB": "  Mirabai ",
            "optionC": "  Tulsidas ",
            "optionD": "  Surdas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChaitanya (1485-1534): Born at Navadwip in Bengal, Chaitanya was the greatest saint of the Bhakti movement. His original name was 'Vishwambhar Mishra'. He was responsible for the popularity of Vaishnavism in Bengal through his Kirtans. He began the Achintayabhedabhedavada School of theology, and preached the religion of intense faith in one Supreme Being whom he called Krishna or Hari. He adored Krishna and Radha and attempted to spiritualize their lives in Vrindavan. ",
            "keyString": "376323s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct about Alvars and Nayanars?\nI. Some of the earliest bhakti movements (c. sixth century) were led by the Alvars (literally, those who are \"immersed\" in devotion to Vishnu) and Nayanars (literally, leaders who were devotees of Shiva).\nII. They travelled from place to place singing hymns in Tamil in praise of their gods.\nIII. During their travels the Alvars and Nayanars identified certain shrines as abodes of their chosen deities",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  I and II ",
            "optionC": "  I and III ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSome of the earliest bhakti movements (c. sixth century) were led by the Alvars (literally, those who are \"immersed\" in devotion to Vishnu) and Nayanars (literally, leaders who were devotees of Shiva). They travelled from place to place singing hymns in Tamil in praise of their gods. During their travels the Alvars and Nayanars identified certain shrines as abodes of their chosen deities. ",
            "keyString": "376344s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the language adopted by the Bhakti saints to preach their ideas to the masses?",
            "optionA": "  Hindi ",
            "optionB": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionC": "  Ardh-Magadhi ",
            "optionD": "  Regional vernacular languages ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhakti movement preached using the local languages so that the message reached the masses. ",
            "keyString": "376366s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Bhakti Saints poem is compiled in Sur Sagar, Sahitva Ratna and Sur Sarawali?",
            "optionA": "  Sur Das ",
            "optionB": "  Kabirdas ",
            "optionC": "  Tulsidas ",
            "optionD": "  Kalidasa ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is commonly held that he was born sometimes in the last quarter of the fifteenth century. His works include Sur Sagar, Sahitva Ratna and Sur Sarawali. In Sur Sagar, Sur Das deals with the life of Krishna\u2019s childhood. He dis\u00adplayed himself not merely as a master of child psychology but also as a devotee of the Almighty. The works and poems of Sur Das exercised tremendous influence on the people and encouraged them to follow the path of Bhakti. ",
            "keyString": "376383s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Bhakti Movement was organised by",
            "optionA": "  Nanak ",
            "optionB": "  Meera ",
            "optionC": "  Ramdas ",
            "optionD": "  Ramanujacharya ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bhakti Movement was started in South India in the 7th century. The earliest seeds of the Bhakti movement in India was organised by Ramanuja. ",
            "keyString": "431048s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Bhakti Saints known as Sri Gauranga, was a popular Vaishnava saint and reformer from Bengal?",
            "optionA": "  Chaitanya ",
            "optionB": "  Mirabai ",
            "optionC": "  Sankaracharya ",
            "optionD": "  Kabir ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChaitanya also known as Sri Gauranga, was a popular Vaishnava saint and reformer from Bengal. He was born of Brahman parents at Nadia. After his education he became a teacher. ",
            "keyString": "431253s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the the founder of the Ramanandi Sampradaya, the largest monastic Hindu renunciant community in modern times?",
            "optionA": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionB": "  Tukaram ",
            "optionC": "  Mirabai ",
            "optionD": "  Kabir ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamananda was a 14th-century Vaishnava devotional poet sant, in the Ganges river region of Northern India. The Hindu tradition recognizes him as the founder of the Ramanandi Sampradaya, the largest monastic Hindu renunciant community in modern times. ",
            "keyString": "431429s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is meant by a 'Pir' in the Sufi tradition?",
            "optionA": "  The Supreme God ",
            "optionB": "  The Guru of the Sufis ",
            "optionC": "  The greatest of all Sufi saints ",
            "optionD": "  The orthodox teacher who contests the Sufi\nbeliefs ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPir or Peer ('elder') is a title for a Sufi master or spiritual guide. They are also referred to as a Hazrat or Shaikh, which is Arabic for Old Man. ",
            "keyString": "431599s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is/are the compositions of Kabir?",
            "optionA": "  Bijak & Sakhi Granth ",
            "optionB": "  Kabir Granthawali& Anurag Sagar ",
            "optionC": "  Only B ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLiterary works with compositions attributed to Kabir include Kabir Bijak, Kabir Parachai, Sakhi Granth, Adi Granth (Sikh), and Kabir Granthawali (Rajasthan). ",
            "keyString": "431762s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following text introduces bhakti marga (the path of faith/devotion) as one of three ways to spiritual freedom and release?",
            "optionA": "  Vedas ",
            "optionB": "  Vedanta ",
            "optionC": "  Brahamans ",
            "optionD": "  Bhagwat Gita ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bhagavad Gita, a post-Vedic scripture composed in 5th to 2nd century BCE, introduces bhakti marga (the path of faith/devotion) as one of three ways to spiritual freedom and release, the other two being karma marga (the path of works) and jnana marga (the path of knowledge). ",
            "keyString": "488918s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Find out the contributions of Bhakti Movement in India:\nI. Surge in vernacular Literature\nII. Development of Philosophies\nIII. Devotional transformation of society and Inclusiveness\nIV. New forms of Worship",
            "optionA": "  I, II & IV ",
            "optionB": "  I, II, III & IV ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & IV ",
            "optionD": "  Only IV ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bhakti movement refers to the theistic devotional trend that emerged in medieval Hinduism. The Bhakti movement regionally developed around different gods and and some sub-religions were Vaishnavism (Vishnu), Shaivism (Shiva), Shaktism (Shakti goddesses), and Smartism. The Bhakti movement witnessed a surge in Hindu literature in regional. Bhakti movement was a devotional transformation of medieval Hindu society, ",
            "keyString": "489133s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the greatest Bhakti poet of Maharasthra?",
            "optionA": "  Ramdas ",
            "optionB": "  Tukaram ",
            "optionC": "  Namdeva ",
            "optionD": "  Eknath ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTukaram, also referred to as Sant Tukaram, Bhakta Tukaram, Tukaram Maharaj, Tukoba and Tukobaraya, was a 17th-century Hindu poet and sant of the Bhakti movement in Maharashtra. Tukaram was the great Marathi Varreni-Vaishnavie sect saint of Bhakti Movement. He composed the famous 'Abhanga poetry'. ",
            "keyString": "489318s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are the basis tenants of Bhakti Movement?",
            "optionA": "  Ideas was the Bhakti movement\u2014devotion to God. Bhakti to God was accepted as salvation ",
            "optionB": "  Ideas were the Bhakti movement\u2014devotion to God with the help of a priest. Bhakti to God was accepted as damnation ",
            "optionC": "  Spiritual sessions in meeting places known as zawiyas, khanqahs, or tekke ",
            "optionD": "  Described as the interiorization, and intensification of human faith and practice ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIdeas was the Bhakti movement\u2014devotion to God. Bhakti to God was accepted as salvation. Ideas was the Bhakti movement\u2014devotion to God with the help of priest. Bhakti to God was accepted as damnation. ",
            "keyString": "489492s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct about the women devotees of the period? I. Karaikkal Ammaiyar, a devotee of Shiva, adopted the path of extreme asceticism in order to attain her goal.II. Andal and Karaikkal Ammaiyar renounced their social obligations, but did not join an alternative order or become nuns.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  none of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKaraikkal Ammaiyar, a devotee of Shiva, adopted the path of extreme asceticism in order to attain her goal. Andal and Karaikkal Ammaiyar renounced their social obligations, but did not join an alternative order or become nuns. ",
            "keyString": "489656s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Bhakti Saints scored a triumph over the Saivas in public debate at the court of Krishna Deva Raya of Vijyanagar?",
            "optionA": "  Guru Nanak ",
            "optionB": "  Chaitanya Maha Prabhu ",
            "optionC": "  Shankaracharya ",
            "optionD": "  Vallabhacharya ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt the court of Krishna Deva Raya of Vijayanagar, Vallabhacharya scored a triumph over the Saivas in public debate. ",
            "keyString": "572809s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the Dadu Dayal or Dadu:\nI. He was a worshipper of Lord Krishna.\nII. He was not for caste or class distinctions and his objective was establishing harmony among all faiths.",
            "optionA": "  I only ",
            "optionB": "  II only ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDadu Dayal (1543-1603) has desired devotion in place of liberation as the ultimate end to be attained. The saints have full faith on sacred text also. Thus, there is a strange harmony in the theories of abstract power and the devotional aspect of the concrete form. ",
            "keyString": "573008s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vishvambhara Mishra was the original name of",
            "optionA": "  Guru Nanak ",
            "optionB": "  Chaitanya Maha Prabhu ",
            "optionC": "  Shankaracharya ",
            "optionD": "  Kabir ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChaitanya (1485-1534): born at Navadwip in Bengal, Chaitanya was the greatest saint of the Bhakti movement. His original name was 'Vishwambhar Mishra'. ",
            "keyString": "573184s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Bhakti Saints of Krishna is a yogi and lover?",
            "optionA": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionB": "  Tukaram ",
            "optionC": "  Mirabai ",
            "optionD": "  Kabir ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMeera, also known as Meera Bai or Mirabai (1498-1546) was a Hindu mystic poet of the Bhakti Movement. She is a celebrated Bhakti saint, particularly in the North Indian Hindu tradition. In her poems, Krishna is a yogi and lover, and she herself is a yogini ready to take her place by his side into a spiritual marital bliss. ",
            "keyString": "573351s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following reason was influenced by the preaching of Bhakti Saints Nimbarka and Vallabhacharya?",
            "optionA": "  Kannada Region ",
            "optionB": "  Telangana Region ",
            "optionC": "  Tamilian Region ",
            "optionD": "  Maratha Region ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Nimbarka and Vallabhacharya were also other preachers of Vaishnavite Bhakti in the Telangana region. ",
            "keyString": "573514s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is related to the concept of Nirguna Brahman?",
            "optionA": "  Advaita ",
            "optionB": "  Visisthadvaita ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  Neither A nor B ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThus, the conception of brahman as a Creator in advaita is a unique one, and directly relates to the advaita views on causality. To resolve such passages in the upanishads, advaita vedanta maintains that really brahman is devoid of all attributes, and is therefore known as nirguna. Brahman may be described as in the upanishads, as Truth (satyam), Knowledge (jnanam), Infinite (anantam), or as Being (sat), Consciousness (cit), Bliss (Ananda), but none of these terms can be truly interpreted as attributes of brahman as a Super-person/God. ",
            "keyString": "621238s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following composed the Hindi version of Ramayana?",
            "optionA": "  Tulsidas ",
            "optionB": "  Valmiki ",
            "optionC": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionD": "  Kabir ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamayana is based on the true story life of Sri Ram. The writer of Ramayan in Hindi is Sant Tulsidas. ",
            "keyString": "621436s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the literal meaning of Bhakti?",
            "optionA": "  Salvation ",
            "optionB": "  Prayer ",
            "optionC": "  Offer words of praise ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe literal meaning of Bhakti is devotion. But the Bhakti movement implied the movement which emphasized intense devotion to God. The saints of the Bhakti movement believed in leading a pure and simple life. The saints emphasized that one need not go to pilgrimages to holy places for securing salvation. ",
            "keyString": "621612s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Bhakti Saint said that \"Abide pure amidst the impurities of the world\"?",
            "optionA": "  Vallabhacharya ",
            "optionB": "  Madhav ",
            "optionC": "  Guru Nanak ",
            "optionD": "  Chaitanya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnother saint-preacher of the time was Guru Nanak, the founder of Sikhism. He was a contemporary of Kabir. He was born in a Khatri family at Talwandi (Nankana Sahib) in the district of Seikhpura in West Punjab, now in Pakistan. He said \"Abide pure amidst the impurities of the world, thus shall thou find the way to religion\". ",
            "keyString": "621778s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous Bhakti Saint who belonged to the royal family of Mewar was",
            "optionA": "  Chaitanya ",
            "optionB": "  Andal ",
            "optionC": "  Meerabai ",
            "optionD": "  Ramabai ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMeera, also known as Meera Bai or Mirabai (1498-1546) was a Hindu mystic poet of the Bhakti movement. She referred to the Lord, whom she saw as her husband, with different names like Satguru, Prabhu Ji, Girdhar Nagar, Krishna. She even called him the husband of her soul. Due to her mother, her in-laws disapproved of her public singing and dancing as she belonged to a Royal Family of Mewar and was a princess. ",
            "keyString": "621937s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said that, the religion was highly practical and sternly ethical?",
            "optionA": "  Chaitanya ",
            "optionB": "  Namadeva ",
            "optionC": "  Guru Nanak ",
            "optionD": "  Kabir ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnother well known saint preacher of the medieval period was Guru Nanak (1469\u22121538). His conception of religion was highly practical and sternly ethical. He exhorted people to give up selfishness, falsehood and hypocrisy and to lead a life of truth, honesty and kindness. ",
            "keyString": "673371s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Bhakti saint opposed cast distinctions and sympathetic towards lower caste in the 6th century AD?",
            "optionA": "  Gnanadev ",
            "optionB": "  Chaitanya ",
            "optionC": "  Namadeva ",
            "optionD": "  Ekanatha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEknath's writings make it clear that there is no caste distinction in the sight of God. ",
            "keyString": "673563s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was/were not disciples of Ramananda?",
            "optionA": "  Kabir & Raidas ",
            "optionB": "  Sena & Sadhana ",
            "optionC": "  Dhanna & Naraharai ",
            "optionD": "  Tulsidas & Mirabai ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHe chose his disciples from all sections of society disregarding caste. His disciples were: a. Kabir, a Muslim weaver b. Raidasa, a cobbler c. Sena, a barber d. Sadhana, a butcher e. Dhanna, a Jat farmer f. Naraharai, a goldsmith g. Pipa, a Rajput prince ",
            "keyString": "673735s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Bhakti Saints was part of the egalitarian, personalized Varkari devotionalism tradition?",
            "optionA": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionB": "  Kabir ",
            "optionC": "  Mirabai ",
            "optionD": "  Tukaram ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHe was part of the egalitarian, personalized Varkari devotionalism tradition. Tukaram is best known for his devotional poetry called Abhanga and community-oriented worship with spiritual songs known as kirtans. His poetry was devoted to Vitthala or Vithoba, an avatar of Hindu god Vishnu. ",
            "keyString": "673898s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct about Bhakti Movement?\nI. The leader of the bhakti movement focusing on the Lord as Rama was Ramananda.\nII. Sri Ramanuja Acharya was an Indian philosopher and is recognized as the most important saint of Sri Vaishnavism",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSri Ramanuja Acharya was an Indian philosopher and is recognized as the most important saint of Sri Vaishnavism. Later developments led by Ramananda created a Rama-oriented movement, now the largest monastic group in Asia. ",
            "keyString": "674060s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote Vedanta-Parijatasourabha, a commentary on the Brahma Sutra, in simple language?",
            "optionA": "  Nimbarka ",
            "optionB": "  Ramanuja ",
            "optionC": "  Madhva ",
            "optionD": "  Vallabhacharya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNimbarka's commentary on the Brahma-Sutras known as the Vedanta-Parijata-Saurabha, and that of his immediate disciple Srinivasa styled the Vedanta-Kaustubha are the chief works of the school of philosophy associated with the name of Nimbarka. The latter is not, however, a mere commentary on the former, as is sometimes wrongly supposed, but a full exposition of the views expressed I the Vedanta-Parijata-Saurabha which is very terse and concise and is not always clear. Both the treatises are therefore essential for the proper understanding of the doctrine of Nimbarka. ",
            "keyString": "723365s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bhakti Saint who was contemporary of Sivaji?",
            "optionA": "  Namadev ",
            "optionB": "  Ekanatha ",
            "optionC": "  Tukaram ",
            "optionD": "  Gnanadeva ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTukaram, also referred to as Sant Tukaram, Bhakta Tukaram, Tukaram Maharaj, Tukoba and Tukobaraya, was a 17th-century Hindu poet and sant of the Bhakti movement in Maharashtra, India. He was part of the egalitarian, personalized Varkari devotionalism tradition. ",
            "keyString": "723578s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kabir was a disciple of",
            "optionA": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionB": "  Ramanujana ",
            "optionC": "  Shakracharya ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKabir is widely believed to have become the first disciple of the Bhakti poet-saint Swami Ramananda in Varanasi, known for devotional Vaishnavism with a strong bent to monist Advaita philosophy teaching that God was inside every person, everything. ",
            "keyString": "723752s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kabir was contemporary of",
            "optionA": "  Guru Nanak ",
            "optionB": "  Sultan Sikandar Lodi ",
            "optionC": "  Both (A) and (B) above ",
            "optionD": "  Babur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKabir was contemporary of both Guru Nanak and Sultan Sikandar Lodi. ",
            "keyString": "723913s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Bhakti Saints writings influenced Hinduism's Bhakti movement and his verses are found in Sikhism's scripture Adi Granth?",
            "optionA": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionB": "  Kabir ",
            "optionC": "  Mirabai ",
            "optionD": "  Tukaram ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKabir was a 15th-century Indian mystic poet and saint, whose writings influenced Hinduism's Bhakti movement and his verses are found in Sikhism's scripture Adi Granth. His early life was in a Muslim family, but he was strongly influenced by his teacher, the Hindu bhakti leader Ramananda. ",
            "keyString": "724073s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who strongly opposed sectarianism and rites and insisted on adoption of Hindi in place of Sanskrit?",
            "optionA": "  Chaitanya ",
            "optionB": "  Ramanuja ",
            "optionC": "  Sankaracharya ",
            "optionD": "  Ramananda ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamananda could not even cast off the sense of superiority of a Hindu over the Mohammedan. Similarly he accepted the superiority of the regenerate classes (dwijas) -over Sudras. Thus Ramananda, like the other saints of the South, did not believe in social equality. He enjoined strict segregation and perfect privacy in the matter of food. Though Ramananda did not believe in the equality of the four varnas and numerous castes, but he made disciples from almost all castes.",
            "keyString": "773879s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which ascetics of the Yoga school of Hindu philosophy influenced the Ramananda?",
            "optionA": "  Kabirpanthi ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna Cult ",
            "optionC": "  Nathpanthi ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTradition asserts that Ramananda developed his philosophy and devotional themes inspired by the south Indian Vedanta philosopher Ramanuja, however evidence also suggests that Ramananda was influenced by Nathpanthi ascetics of the Yoga school of Hindu philosophy. ",
            "keyString": "773930s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Different Sufi schools or orders in India were known as",
            "optionA": "  Khangahs ",
            "optionB": "  Qalandars ",
            "optionC": "  Silsilahs ",
            "optionD": "  Darveshs ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSilsila is an Arabic word meaning chain, link, connection often used in various senses of lineage. In particular, it may be translated as \"(religious) order\" or \"spiritual genealogy\" where one Sufi Master transfers his khilfat to his spiritual. Silsilas originated with the initiation of Sufi orders which dates back to the Islamic prophet Muhammad. ",
            "keyString": "774079s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The earliest Sufi order to arrive in India was",
            "optionA": "  Chisti ",
            "optionB": "  Suhrawardy ",
            "optionC": "  Qadiri ",
            "optionD": "  Naqshbandi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was the first of the four main Sufi orders (Chishti, Qadiriyya, Suhrawardiyya and Naqshbandi) to be established in this region. Moinuddin Chishti introduced the Chishti Order in Lahore (Punjab) and Ajmer (Rajasthan), sometime in the middle of the 12th century CE. ",
            "keyString": "774196s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chaitanya Mahaprabhu was an ascetic Hindu monk and social reformer in 16th century was from",
            "optionA": "  Bihar ",
            "optionB": "  Assam ",
            "optionC": "  Orissa ",
            "optionD": "  Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChaitanya Mahaprabhu was an ascetic Hindu monk and social reformer in 16th century Bengal. A great proponent of loving devotion for God, bhakti yoga, Chaitanya worshiped the Lord in the form of Krishna. ",
            "keyString": "774303s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded the faith on a ritual-free, simple \"Sat Shri Akal\" or the worship of God and truth?",
            "optionA": "  Dadu Dayal ",
            "optionB": "  Guru Nanak ",
            "optionC": "  Sri Chaitanya ",
            "optionD": "  Guru Govind Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe founder of Sikhism, Guru Nanak (1469-1538), was one of the best preachers and reformers in medieval India. He was critical of idol worship, pilgrimages, caste differences and the ceremonial frills of religion. Nanak founded his faith on a ritual-free, simple \u201cSat Shri Akal\u201d or the worship of God and truth. ",
            "keyString": "821596s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following aspects is not common to both Bhakti movement and Sufi movement?",
            "optionA": "  Personal love for God ",
            "optionB": "  Worship of idols ",
            "optionC": "  Mysticism ",
            "optionD": "  Visit to holy shrines ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth Bhaktism and Sufism laid stress on the direct communion of Soul with the God and disregarded formal worships and practices like idol-worship, pilgrimages, bathing in holy rivers. ",
            "keyString": "821798s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Select the correct statement related to the Bhakti Movement in Medieval History in India",
            "optionA": "  To the theistic devotional trend that emerged in medieval Hinduism and later revolutionised in Buddhism ",
            "optionB": "  To the theistic devotional trend that emerged in medieval Hinduism and later revolutionised in Jainism ",
            "optionC": "  To the theistic devotional trend that emerged in medieval Hinduism and later revolutionised in Sikhism ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bhakti movement refers to the theistic devotional trend that emerged in medieval Hinduism and later revolutionised in Sikhism. The Bhakti movement regionally developed around different gods and goddesses, and some sub-religions were Vaishnavism (Vishnu), Shaivism (Shiva), Shaktism (Shakti goddesses), and Smartism. ",
            "keyString": "821976s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the name of the The collection of hymns of Alvar Saints?",
            "optionA": "  Divya Prabandha ",
            "optionB": "  Tamil Veda ",
            "optionC": "  Kabir Wani ",
            "optionD": "  Granthawali ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe collection of their hymns is known as Divya Prabandha. The Bhakti literature that sprang from Alvars has contributed to the establishment and sustenance of a culture that broke away from the ritual-oriented Vedic religion and rooted itself in devotion as the only path for salvation. ",
            "keyString": "822146s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Sufi Sect' originated and developed in",
            "optionA": "  Islam ",
            "optionB": "  Christianity ",
            "optionC": "  Hinduism ",
            "optionD": "  Zoroastrianism ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe exact origin of Sufism is disputed. Some sources state that Sufism is the inner dimensions of the teachings of Muhammad whereas others say that Sufism emerged during the Islamic Golden Age from about the 8th to 10th centuries. ",
            "keyString": "822310s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Sufi's dargah is at Ajmer?",
            "optionA": "  Baba Farid ",
            "optionB": "  Qutbdin Bakhtiyar Kaki ",
            "optionC": "  Moinuddin Chisti ",
            "optionD": "  Khwaja Bahuddin ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMoinuddin Chishti located at Ajmer, Rajasthan, India. The shrine has the grave (Maqbara) of the revered saint, Moinuddin Chisti. ",
            "keyString": "921474s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct definition of Nirguna?",
            "optionA": "  It is the concept of a formless God ",
            "optionB": "  It is the concept of a formless Guru ",
            "optionC": "  It is the concept of spirituality ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMetaphysical concept of God in Hinduism, Gods general ultimate form/nature is formless pure consciousness (Nirakar Nirguna/without form/Impersonal) but it can manifests into divine form (Sakar Saugna/with form/personal). God has the ability to manifest into any kind of form and shape. ",
            "keyString": "921527s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was the basic premise of Bhakti Movement?",
            "optionA": "  Bhakti or Single minded, uninterrupted and extreme devotion to God with the help of Brahmins was the only means of Salvation ",
            "optionB": "  Bhakti or Single minded, uninterrupted and extreme devotion to God was the only means of Salvation ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe mystic Saints of medieval India were the exponents of the Bhakti movement. They were not affiliated to any particular sect. They had no blind faith in any sacred scriptures, no device to set up separate sects, no loyalty to any particular creed. They attained greatness without following any ritual or ceremonies and through individual exertion. The exponents of Bhakti movement condemned idolatry and believed in monotheism. They thought that Bhakti or Single minded, uninterrupted and extreme devotion to God was the only means of Salvation. ",
            "keyString": "921669s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sufism the liberal and mystic movement of Islam, reached India in the __________ century?",
            "optionA": "  11th ",
            "optionB": "  12th ",
            "optionC": "  14th ",
            "optionD": "  13 th ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSufism found its way into India during the eleventh and twelfth centuries when many Sufi saints came to India particularly in Multan and Lahore of the Punjab. The most celebrated of these Sufi saints was Khwaja Muinuddin Chisti who came to Lahore from Ghazni in 1161 and settled in Ajmer under Prithviraj. ",
            "keyString": "921792s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct about the early traditions of Bhakti?\nI. In the course of the evolution of forms of worship, in many instances, poet-saints emerged as leaders around whom there developed a community of devotees.\nII. Brahmanas remained important intermediaries between gods and devotees in several forms of bhakti.\nIII. At a different level, historians of religion often classify bhakti traditions into two broad categories: saguna (with attributes) and nirguna (without attributes)",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  I and II ",
            "optionC": "  I and III ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe early traditions of Bhakti were In the course of the evolution of forms of worship, in many instances, poet-saints emerged as leaders around whom there developed a community of devotees, Brahmanas remained important intermediaries between gods and devotees in several forms of bhakti, At a different level, historians of religion often classify bhakti traditions into two broad categories: saguna (with attributes) and nirguna (without attributes). ",
            "keyString": "921902s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was among the following Bhakti saints gave a new orientation of Hinduism through his doctrine of Advaita or Monism?",
            "optionA": "  Ramanuja ",
            "optionB": "  Sankara ",
            "optionC": "  Guru Nanak ",
            "optionD": "  Chaitanya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the ninth century Sankara started a Hindu revivalist movement giving a new orientation to Hinduism. He was born in Kaladi in Kerala. His doctrine of Advaita or Monism was too abstract to appeal to the common man. ",
            "keyString": "985245s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following had given the doctrine of Advaita or Monism?",
            "optionA": "  Sankara ",
            "optionB": "  Saivaite Nayanmars ",
            "optionC": "  Vashnavaite Alwars ",
            "optionD": "  Tukaram ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSankara is regarded as the promoter of Advaita Ved\u0101nta as a distinct school of Indian philosophy, the origins of this school predate Sankara. The existence of an Advaita tradition is acknowledged by Sankara in his commentaries. ",
            "keyString": "985294s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Bhakti saint preached the concept of Vishishtadvaita?",
            "optionA": "  Sankara ",
            "optionB": "  Ramanuja ",
            "optionC": "  Madhava ",
            "optionD": "  Nimbarka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamanuja, the main proponent of Vishishtadvaita philosophy contends that the Prasthanatrayi (\"The three courses\"), namely the Upanishads, the Bhagavad Gita, and the Brahma Sutras are to be interpreted in a way that shows this unity in diversity, for any other way would violate their consistency. Vedanta Desika defines Vishishtadvaita using the statement, Asesha Chit-Achit Prakaaram Brahmaikameva Tatvam : Brahman, as qualified by the sentient and insentient modes (or attributes), is the only reality. ",
            "keyString": "985426s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important saint of the Bhakti Movement in Maharashtra who was born at Satara and is said to have died in Punjab, was",
            "optionA": "  Jnanesvar ",
            "optionB": "  Namadeva ",
            "optionC": "  Tukaram ",
            "optionD": "  Guru Ramdas ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNamdev, also transliterated as Nam Dayv, Namdeo,Namadeva, (traditionally, c.\u20091270 \u2013 c.\u20091350) was a poet and a saint from Maharashtra, India who is significant to the Varkari sect of Hinduism. Bhagat Namdev's writings were also recognized by the \"Gurus\" of Sikhism and are included in the holy book of Sikhism, the Sri Guru Granth Sahib. Namdev worship lord Vitthal that is one of the name of lord Vishnu. ",
            "keyString": "985545s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Pandharpur Movement is associated with the Bhakti Movement of",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Both (a) and (c) ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Pandharpur Movement is associated with the Bhakti Movement of Maharashtra. The spread of the Bhakti movement in Maharashtra inculcated the spirit of oneness among the Marathas. The main teachings of the leaders were Bhakti or devotion to God and equality of all believers before God without any distinction of class or birth. The Bhakti movement united the people of Maharashtra in a common love of man and faith in one God. ",
            "keyString": "985656s58m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the social impact of Bhakti Movement in Indian Society.\nI. The Bhakti movement was a devotional transformation of medieval Hindu society, wherein Vedic rituals or alternatively ascetic monk-like lifestyle for moksha gave way to individualistic loving relationship with a personally defined god.\nII. Bhakti movement provided women and members of the Shudra and untouchable communities an inclusive path to spiritual salvation.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bhakti movement was a devotional transformation of medieval Hindu society, wherein Vedic rituals or alternatively ascetic monk-like lifestyle for moksha gave way to individualistic loving relationship with a personally defined god. Salvation which was previously considered attainable only by men of Brahmin, Kshatriya and Vaishya castes, became available to everyone. Most scholars state that Bhakti movement provided women and members of the Shudra and untouchable communities an inclusive path to spiritual salvation. Some scholars disagree that the Bhakti movement was premised on such social inequalities. ",
            "keyString": "47913s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Bhakti Saint created Vinaya-Patrika and Kavitavali?",
            "optionA": "  Chaitanya ",
            "optionB": "  Shankar Dev ",
            "optionC": "  Tulsidas ",
            "optionD": "  Narasi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn his works Kavitavali and Vinayapatrika, Tulsidas attests to his parents abandoning him after birth due to an inauspicious astrological configuration. ",
            "keyString": "47958s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Bhakti Saints blended that the philosophical monist of the past with stress on Bhakti, the poetry and dignity of Valmiki's Ramayana with the devotional fervour and humanism of Bhagvata?",
            "optionA": "  Sur Das ",
            "optionB": "  Kabirdas ",
            "optionC": "  Tulsidas ",
            "optionD": "  Kalidasa ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTulsi Das was a humanist and universalist and laid stress upon knowledge, devotion, worship and mediation. He has blended in his work the philosophical monist of the past with stress on Bhakti, the poetry and dignity of Valmiki\u2019s Ramayana with the devotional fervour and humanism of Bhagvata. ",
            "keyString": "47978s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following dynasties under the Saivaite Nayanmars and Vashnavaite Alwars preached the Bhakti cult?",
            "optionA": "  Pallavas, Pandyas and Cholas ",
            "optionB": "  Pallavas, Kaktyas and Cholas ",
            "optionC": "  Pallavas, Pandyas and Cheras ",
            "optionD": "  Rashtrakutas, Pandyas and Cholas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPallavas, Pandyas and Cholas dynasties under the Saivaite Nayanmars and Vashnavaite Alwars preached the Bhakti cult. ",
            "keyString": "47994s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the famous Sufi saint whose mausoleum was erected at Fatehpur Sikri.",
            "optionA": "  Nizamuddin Auliya ",
            "optionB": "  Sheikh Muin-ud-din Chisti ",
            "optionC": "  Baba Farid-ud-din ",
            "optionD": "  Sheikh Salim Chisti ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne of the finest examples of Mughal architecture and a noted religious centre for Muslims is the Dargah or Tomb of Sheikh Salim Chisti in Fatehpur Sikri. Emperor Akbar had this tomb built in the honour of Sufi Saint Salim Chisti between 1571 and 1580. ",
            "keyString": "48009s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which century Bhakti movement began?",
            "optionA": "  6th century ",
            "optionB": "  7th century ",
            "optionC": "  8th century ",
            "optionD": "  9th century ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bhakti movement refers to the theistic devotional trend that emerged in medieval Hinduism and later revolutionised in Sikhism. It originated in seventh-century south India (now Tamil Nadu and Kerala), and spread northwards. ",
            "keyString": "98022s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The concept of Sagunabrahmana was the outcome of which concept of Bhakti Movement?",
            "optionA": "  Nirgunabraman ",
            "optionB": "  Vaishanavism ",
            "optionC": "  Shaivism ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bhakti movement of Hinduism saw two ways of imaging the nature of the divine (Brahman) \u2013 Nirguna and Saguna. Nirguna Brahman was the concept of the Ultimate Reality as formless, without attributes or quality. ",
            "keyString": "98064s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was saint kabir born?",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Varanasi ",
            "optionC": "  Mathura ",
            "optionD": "  Hyderabad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKabir, (Arabic: \"Great\") (born 1440, Varanasi, Jaunpur, India-died 1518, Maghar), iconoclastic Indian poet-saint revered by Hindus, Muslims, and Sikhs. The birth of Kabir remains shrouded in mystery and legend. ",
            "keyString": "98085s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who preaches Vishishtadvaita?",
            "optionA": "  Tulsidas ",
            "optionB": "  Saivaite Nayanmars ",
            "optionC": "  Sankara ",
            "optionD": "  Ramanuja ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamanujacharya is famous as the chief proponent of Vishishtadvaita subschool of Vedanta, and his disciples were likely authors of texts such as the Shatyayaniya Upanishad. Ramanujacharya himself wrote influential texts, such as bhasya on the Brahma Sutras and the Bhagavad Gita, all in Sanskrit. ",
            "keyString": "98102s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the Guru of Kabir?",
            "optionA": "  Ramanuja ",
            "optionB": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionC": "  Vallabhacharya ",
            "optionD": "  Namadeva ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKabir is widely believed to have become the first disciple of the Bhakti poet-saint Swami Ramananda in Varanasi, known for devotional Vaishnavism with a strong bent to monist Advaita philosophy teaching that God was inside every person, everything. ",
            "keyString": "98118s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following cult was popularised by Chaitanya?",
            "optionA": "  Shiva Cult ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna Cult ",
            "optionC": "  Eknathwad ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChaitanya is said to have travelled all over India in spreading the Krishna Cult. ",
            "keyString": "141679s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct about the attitudes of Alvars and Nayanars towards caste system? \nI. Alvars and Nayanars initiated a movement of protest against the caste system and the dominance of Brahmanas or at least attempted to reform the system.\nII. Alvars and Nayanars always supported the caste system in the society.\nIII. The importance of the traditions of the Alvars and Nayanars was sometimes indicated by the claim that their compositions were as important as the Vedas",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  I and II ",
            "optionC": "  I and III ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlvars and Nayanars initiated a movement of protest against the caste system and the dominance of Brahmanas or at least attempted to reform the system.II. Alvars and Nayanars always supported the caste system in the society. The importance of the traditions of the Alvars and Nayanars was sometimes indicated by the claim that their compositions were as important as the Vedas. ",
            "keyString": "141904s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Saivaite Nayanmars and Vashanavaite Alwar preached the Bhakti Cult under which of the following rulers?",
            "optionA": "  Pallavas, Pandyas and Cholas ",
            "optionB": "  Pallavas, Cheras and Rashtrakutas ",
            "optionC": "  Pallavas, Vijaynagar and Bahmani Kingdoms ",
            "optionD": "  Cheras & Pandavas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPallavas, Pandyas and Cholas. ",
            "keyString": "142125s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sundar Vilas is the work of a famous Bhakti Saint",
            "optionA": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionB": "  Guru Nanak ",
            "optionC": "  Dadu ",
            "optionD": "  Tukaram ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDadu uses a lot of Persian, Punjabi, Sindhi and Gujarati words in his writings. He was well versed with Persian and his most famous work is Sundar Vilas. ",
            "keyString": "142311s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote biography of Chaitanya?",
            "optionA": "  Krishnadasa Kaviraja ",
            "optionB": "  Namadeva ",
            "optionC": "  Shankar Dev ",
            "optionD": "  Both A & B ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKrishna Dasa Kaviraja Goswami (born 1496; date of death unknown) was the author of the Chaitanya Charitamrita, a hagiography on the life of the mystic and saint Chaitanya Mahaprabhu (1486\u20131533), who is considered by the Gaudiya Vaishnava school of Hinduism to be an incarnation of Radha and Krishna combined. ",
            "keyString": "142499s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are not correct about Bhagavatism and Krishna Cult (Bhakti Cult)?\nI. Bhagavatism is a branch of Vaishnavism, where the devotees worship the various avatars of Lord Vishnu.\nII. The origin of Bhagavatism or Vaishnavism has been sought in the Upanishadic period because in the 'Chandogya Upanishad' Krishna is described as a disciple of the sage Ghora.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhagavatism or Krishnaism is a religious creed in Hinduism. The followers of the creed are devoted towards Lord Krishna. Bhagavatism is a branch of Vaishnavism, where the devotees worships the various avatars of Lord Vishnu. ",
            "keyString": "207576s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is associated with Sufi saints?",
            "optionA": "  Tripitaka ",
            "optionB": "  Dakhma ",
            "optionC": "  Khanjah ",
            "optionD": "  Synagogue ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhanjah is a place meant for sufi brotherhood gathering. It is a place for spiritual retreat and character reformation. It is also know as 'Ribat'. ",
            "keyString": "207785s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is correct about Alvar Saints?",
            "optionA": "  The twelve Alvars were Tamil poet-saints, who lived between 6th and 9th centuries AD and espoused 'emotional devotion' or bhakti to Visnu-Krishna in their songs ",
            "optionB": "  The 63 Alvars saints were the Shiva devotional poets, who lived between 5th and 10th centuries ",
            "optionC": "  Only B ",
            "optionD": "  Both A & B ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe alvars, also spelt as alwars or azhwars were Tamil poet-saints of South India who espoused bhakti (devotion) to the Hindu god Vishnu or his avatar Krishna in their songs of longing, ecstasy and service. ",
            "keyString": "207964s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Bhakti Saint popularised Vaishnava cult in Gujarat?",
            "optionA": "  Chaitanya ",
            "optionB": "  Narasi ",
            "optionC": "  Tulsidas ",
            "optionD": "  Sankar Dev ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe original name of Narasi was Narasimha Mehta. He popularised Vaishnava cult in Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "208139s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Select the correct order",
            "optionA": "  Nizamuddin Auliya, Kabir, Mirabai, Tulsidas ",
            "optionB": "  Mirabai, Kabir Nizamuddin Auliya, Tulsidas ",
            "optionC": "  Kabir, Nizamuddin Auliya, Tulsidas, Mirabai ",
            "optionD": "  Tulsidas, Mirabai, Kabir, Nizamuddin Auliya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNizamuddin Auliya (1238-1325) (Hazrat Nizamuddin)(famous sufi Saint of chisti Order) > Kabir (1440-1518) (Poet and Saint of Bhakti Movement) > Meerabai (1498-1574) (a Hindu poetess and elevate of lord Krishna) > Tulsidas (1511-1623) (He was contemporary of Mughal Emperor Akbar he wrote (Ramcharitmanas). ",
            "keyString": "208312s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What the term 'Bhakti' refers to?",
            "optionA": "  Bhakti is derived from the root bhaj, which means \"divide, share, partake, participate, to belong to\" ",
            "optionB": "  Bhakti is derived from the root bhaj, which means collaboration ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  Only B ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Sanskrit word bhakti is derived from the root bhaj, which means \"divide, share, partake, participate, to belong to\". The word also means \"attachment, devotion to, fondness for, homage, faith or love, worship, piety to something as a spiritual, religious principle or means of salvation\". ",
            "keyString": "295580s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following causes Bhakti Movement in India?",
            "optionA": "  Caste Division ",
            "optionB": "  Untouchability ",
            "optionC": "  Ritualism ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bhakti movement originated as a reaction against caste division, untouchability, and ritualism in India. One of the important landmark in the cultural history of medieval India was the silent revolution in society brought about by by some socio-religious reformers, known as the Bhakti Movement. ",
            "keyString": "295827s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Bhakti Saint propounded Suddhadvaita Vedanta (Pure non-dualism) and philosophy called Pustimarga (the path of grace)?",
            "optionA": "  Ramanuja ",
            "optionB": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionC": "  Vallabhacharya ",
            "optionD": "  Narasi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVallabhacharya was born in Varanasi. He propounded Suddhadvaita Vedanta (Pure non-dualism) and philosophy called Pustimarga (the path of grace). He was the founder of a school called Rudra Sampradaya. ",
            "keyString": "296044s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sankardeva was a great bhakti saint of",
            "optionA": "  Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Assam ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSrimanta Sankardeva Or Mahapurush Srimanta Sankardeva - Vaisnav Saint of Assam Mahapurush Srimanta Sankardeva was born in 1449 into Baro-Bhuyans family near at Aali-pukhuri, about 8 miles to the west-north-west of Bardowa situated in the Nagaon district of Assam. ",
            "keyString": "296258s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following aspects of Bhakti Movement was common with Sufism?",
            "optionA": "  Monotheism or belief in one God ",
            "optionB": "  Equality and brotherhood of man ",
            "optionC": "  Rejection of rituals and class Division ",
            "optionD": "  All of the Above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMonotheism or belief in one God, Equality and brotherhood of man, Rejection of rituals and class division are aspect of Bhakti Movement that was common with Sufism. ",
            "keyString": "296467s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Bhakti Saints was responsible for founding many punyakshetras along the length and breadth of India, by taming avatars of Parvati and imprisoning her essence in Sri Chakras?",
            "optionA": "  Shankaracharya ",
            "optionB": "  Ramanada Saraswati ",
            "optionC": "  Tulsidas ",
            "optionD": "  Valmiki ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShankaracharya Bhakti Saints was responsible for founding many punyakshetram along the length and breadth of India, by taming avatars of Parvati and imprisoning her essence in Sri Chakras. ",
            "keyString": "368193s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Find out the correct statement (s) related to the features of Bhakti Movement?\nI. Its proponents preached the 'unity of the god-head' and emphasized that 'devotion to God' and faith in him led to salvation.\nII. It laid stress on equality of all human beings and universal brotherhood.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Bhakti Movement, God is one, He alone should be worshipped. By following the path of true devotion (Bhakti) one can find salvation or (nijat, mukti).A true guru is indispensable for realizing God or attaining salvation. All men are equal and there is no question of superiority or inferiority among men. There is brotherhood of mankind. The image worship and caste distinctions and class hatred were the worst enemies of man. They strongly denounced useless ceremonies and rituals and rites must be given up. They are unnecessary and do not help persons to attain salvation. Only the good actions of man can help him to attain salvation. ",
            "keyString": "368394s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Select the correct statement (s) related to the Vallabhacharya: I. His doctrine came to be known as \"Pushti Marga\" for his successors laid stress on the physical side of Krishna's sports.\nII. He is the founder of the International Society for Krishna Consciousness or ISKCON, commonly called the \"Hare Krishnas\"",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn spite of Vallabha's stress on self-control and renunciation, his doctrine came to be known as \u201cPushti Marga\u201d for his successors laid stress on the physical side of Krishna's sports so that the creed came to be called as the \u201cEpicureanism of the East\u201c. ",
            "keyString": "368575s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Bhakti Saint did not believe in the qualified monism of Ramanuja and emphasised the doctrine of duality, based mainly upon the Bhagavata Purana?",
            "optionA": "  Madhava ",
            "optionB": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionC": "  Vallabhacharya ",
            "optionD": "  Chaitnaya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadhava did not believe in the qualified monism of Ramanuja and emphasised the doctrine of duality, based mainly upon the Bhagavata Purana. ",
            "keyString": "368759s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of the Bhakti Movement in Maharashtra in 13th Century?",
            "optionA": "  Namadev ",
            "optionB": "  Ekanatha ",
            "optionC": "  Tukaram ",
            "optionD": "  Gnanadeva ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGnanadevawas the founder of the Bhakti Movement in Maharashtra in the thirteenth century. It was called Maharashtradharma. He wrote a commentary of Bhagavat Gita called Gnaneswari. ",
            "keyString": "368933s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the writer of Rukmini Swayamwar Hastamalak, which was comprised 764 owees and based on a 14-shlok Sanskrit hymn with the same name by Shankaracharya?",
            "optionA": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionB": "  Eknath ",
            "optionC": "  Mirabai ",
            "optionD": "  Tukaram ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEknath wrote Rukmini Swayamwar Hastamalak, which was comprised 764 owees and based on a 14-shlok Sanskrit hymn with the same name by Shankaracharya. ",
            "keyString": "431217s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which statement (s) is/are correct related to the Ramananda?\nI. He worshipped Ram and Sita but preached the oneness of God and the doctrine of Bhakti for everyone\nII. Dismissed the caste system and untouchability, simplified rules of worship and made rigidity of the Varnashrama tradition milder",
            "optionA": "  I only ",
            "optionB": "  II only ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamananda was born at Allahabad. He was originally a follower of Ramanuja. Later he founded his own sect and preached his principles in Hindi at Banaras and Agra. He was a worshipper of Rama. He was the first to employ the vernacular medium to propagate his ideas. Simplification of worship and emancipation of people from the traditional caste rules were his two important contributions to the Bhakti movement. He opposed the caste system and chose his disciples from all sections of society disregarding caste.",
            "keyString": "431456s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was the reformer and philosopher from Ramanandi Sampradaya in the lineage of Jagadguru Ramanandacharya renowned for his devotion to the Lord Shri Rama?",
            "optionA": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionB": "  Tukaram ",
            "optionC": "  Valmiki ",
            "optionD": "  Tulsidas ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTulsidas also known as Goswami Tulsidas was a Hindu Vaishnava saint and poet, often called reformer and philosopher from Ramanandi Sampradaya, in the lineage of Jagadguru Ramanandacharya renowned for his devotion to the Lord Shri Rama. ",
            "keyString": "431661s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the cardinal principle of Bhakti Cult?\nI. It was influencing devotion to a personal God, whose grace was the only means of attaining salvation or Mukti.\nII. It stressed the idea of a personal God and pointed out the absurdity of the caste system in the presence of God and the futility of external rites and ceremonies.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe cardinal principle of Bhakti Cult was influencing devotion to a personal God, whose grace was the only means of attaining salvation or Mukti. It stressed the idea of a personal God and pointed out the absurdity of the caste system in the presence of God and the futility of external rites and ceremonies. It allowed both men and women to achieve salvation by Bhakti. God is one, He alone should be worshipped. By following the path of true devotion (Bhakti) one can find salvation or (nijat, mukti).A true guru is indispensable for realizing God or attaining salvation. ",
            "keyString": "431851s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Select the correct statement (s) with reference to the Bhakti Movement",
            "optionA": "  Collection of Alvar Saints hymns is known as Divya Prabandha ",
            "optionB": "  Compilation of Alvar Saints poetry / literature Tirumurai is called \"Tamil Veda\" ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe collection of their hymns is known as Divya Prabandha. All the saints were male except one named Andal. The 63 Nayanars saints were the Shiva devotional poets, who lived between 5th and 10th centuries. ",
            "keyString": "432044s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Bhakti sect founded by Birbhan and their religious granth is revered like the Granth of the Sikhs?",
            "optionA": "  Pothi ",
            "optionB": "  Satnamis ",
            "optionC": "  Vaishanavism ",
            "optionD": "  Shaivism ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sect founded by Birbhan is known as Satnamis and their religious granth is known as Pothi, which is revered like the Granth of the Sikhs. ",
            "keyString": "482826s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Select the incorrect statement (s) about Bhakti Saint Ramananda.\nI.\u00a0He advocated prabattimarga or path of self-surrender to God.\nII.\u00a0He propagated 'Dvaita or dualism of Jivatma and Paramatma'.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamananda was a 14th-century Vaishnava devotional poet sant, in the Ganges river region of Northern India. The Hindu tradition recognizes him as the founder of the Ramanandi Sampradaya, the largest monastic Hindu renunciant community in modern times. ",
            "keyString": "483053s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following propagated Dvaita or dualism of Jivatma and Paramatma?",
            "optionA": "  Vallabhacharya ",
            "optionB": "  Madhava ",
            "optionC": "  Merabai ",
            "optionD": "  Nimbarka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadhava propagated Dvaita or dualism of Jivatma and Paramatma. According to his philosophy, the world is not an illusion but a reality. God, soul, matter are unique in nature. ",
            "keyString": "483232s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rudra Sampradaya School was founded by",
            "optionA": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionB": "  Vallabhacharya ",
            "optionC": "  Narasi ",
            "optionD": "  Chaitanya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRudra Sampradaya School was founded by Vallabhacharya. ",
            "keyString": "483397s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Bhakti Saint emphasised the essential oneness of all religion by describing Hindus and Muslims 'as pots of the same clay'?",
            "optionA": "  Kabir ",
            "optionB": "  Tulsidas ",
            "optionC": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionD": "  Raidasa ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKabir emphasised the essential oneness of all religions by describing Hindus and Muslims \u2018as pots of the same clay\u2019. To him Rama and Allah, temple and mosque were the same. He regarded devotion to god as an effective means of salvation and urged that to achieve this one must have a pure heart, free from cruelty, dishonesty, hypocrisy and insincerity. He is regarded as the greatest of the mystic saints and his followers are called Kabirpanthis.",
            "keyString": "483571s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote Dasa Sloki, which deals with three realities (tri-tattava) --Brahma (Krishna), soul (Chit) and matter (Achit)?",
            "optionA": "  Nimbarka ",
            "optionB": "  Ramanuja ",
            "optionC": "  Madhva ",
            "optionD": "  Vallabhacharya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNimbarkacharya in his commentary in 'Dashashloki' dealt with three realities: Brahma(the supreme reality), soul(chit) and matter(achit). ",
            "keyString": "551539s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following preached gospel of love?",
            "optionA": "  Gnandeva ",
            "optionB": "  Namadev ",
            "optionC": "  Ekanath ",
            "optionD": "  Kabir ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNamdev preached the sublime gospel of love and devotion and liberated the people from the shackles of rituals and caste system. ",
            "keyString": "551580s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Bhakti Cult preached under the Pallavas, Pandyas and Cholas?",
            "optionA": "  Saivaite Nayanmars ",
            "optionB": "  Vashnavaite Alwars ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  Advaita ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Saivaite Nayanmars and Vashnavaite Alwars preached the Bhakti cult under the Pallavas, Pandyas and Cholas. But, the spread of Bhakti movement in medieval India is a different kind. This medieval Bhakti movement was the direct result of the influence of the spread of Islam in India. ",
            "keyString": "551601s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which saint and reformer of Bengal who popularized the Krishna Cult?",
            "optionA": "  Vallabhacharya ",
            "optionB": "  Madhava ",
            "optionC": "  Chaitanya ",
            "optionD": "  Nimbarka ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChaitanya means \"consciousness\"; Maha means \"Great\" and Prabhu means \"Lord\" or \"Master\". Chaitanya was born as the second son of Jagannath Mishra and his wife Sachi Devi. Jagannath's family lived in the village of Dhakadakshin, Golapganj, Srihatta, Bengal. According to Chaitanya Charitamruta, Chaitanya was born on the full moon night of 18 February 1486, at the time of a lunar eclipse. Alternatively, Chaitanya is also believed to born in Mayapur. Mayapur is located on the banks of the Ganges river, at the point of its confluence with the Jalangi, near Nabadwip, West Bengal, India, 130 km north of Kolkata (Calcutta). Mayapur is considered a holy place by a number of other traditions within Hinduism. ",
            "keyString": "551619s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Bhakti saint of Maharashtra responsible for creating a background for Maratha nationalism and also opposed all social distinctions?",
            "optionA": "  Gnandeva ",
            "optionB": "  Namadev ",
            "optionC": "  Ekanath ",
            "optionD": "  Tukaram ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnother Bhakti saint of Maharashtra was Tukaram, a contemporary of Sivaji. He was responsible for creating a background for Maratha nationalism. He opposed all social distinctions. The importance of women in society was also increased because the Bhakti movement gave equal importance to them. ",
            "keyString": "551635s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Sufi Saint, contemporary of Prithviraj Chauhan, was",
            "optionA": "  Khwaja Muinuddin Chisti ",
            "optionB": "  Sheikh Salim Chisti ",
            "optionC": "  Sheikh Nizamuddin Auliya ",
            "optionD": "  Baba Farid ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhwaja Muinuddin Chisti is regarded as foremost preacher of Sufism among Sufis of India. Akbar, the Mughal emperor believed that it was his blessings which lead him a son and the heir for the Mughal throne. ",
            "keyString": "661215s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote Shiksha Ashtak which was called as the cream of the Shastras?",
            "optionA": "  Mirabai ",
            "optionB": "  Tulsidas ",
            "optionC": "  Kabir ",
            "optionD": "  Chaitanya ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChaitanya wrote Shiksha Ashtak in which he gave the cream of the Shastras. ",
            "keyString": "661260s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sri Ramanuja Acharya was an Indian philosopher and is recognized as the most important saint of",
            "optionA": "  Sri Vaishnavism ",
            "optionB": "  Sri Vaishavism ",
            "optionC": "  Nirguna ",
            "optionD": "  Sikkhism ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSri Ramanuja Acharya was an Indian philosopher and is recognized as the most important saint of Sri Vaishnavism. His philosophical foundations for devotionalism were influential to the Bhakti movement. ",
            "keyString": "661281s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following concept the Bhakti movement of Hinduism saw two ways of imaging the nature of the divine (Brahman)?",
            "optionA": "  Nirguna and Saguna ",
            "optionB": "  Shaivism ",
            "optionC": "  Sikkhism ",
            "optionD": "  Jainism ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bhakti movement of Hinduism saw two ways of imaging the nature of the divine (Brahman) \u2013 Nirguna and Saguna. Nirguna Brahman was the concept of the Ultimate Reality as formless, without attributes or quality. ",
            "keyString": "661301s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Sufi saint who maintained that devotional music was one way of moving closer to God was",
            "optionA": "  Muin-ud-din-Chisti ",
            "optionB": "  Baba Farid ",
            "optionC": "  Saiyid Mummed ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Alam Bukhari ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBaba Farid also knows as Khwaja Fariduddin was a sufi preacher and poet of 12th century. He is considered as the first poet of Punjabi Language. He found that \"music is the way of reaching God\". ",
            "keyString": "661318s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who exhorted people to give up selfishness, falsehood and hypocrisy and to lead a life of truth, honesty and kindness?",
            "optionA": "  Vallabhacharya ",
            "optionB": "  Guru Nanak ",
            "optionC": "  Kabir ",
            "optionD": "  Nimbarka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGuru Nanak (1469\u22121538) Another well known saint preacher of the medieval period was Guru Nanak, founder of the Sikh. He exhorted people to give up selfishness, falsehood and hypocrisy and to lead a life of truth, honesty and kindness. ",
            "keyString": "742150s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote a commentry of Bhagvat Gita called Gnaneswari?",
            "optionA": "  Gnandeva ",
            "optionB": "  Namadev ",
            "optionC": "  Ekanath ",
            "optionD": "  Both A & B ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGnanadeva wrote a commentary of Bhagavad Gita called Gnaneswari. ",
            "keyString": "742203s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which statement (s) is/are correct related to the Kabir.\nI. He was the disciple of Ramananda and the most liberal among medieval Indian reformers.\nII. He was possibly a contemporary of Sultan Muhammad Bin Tughlaq (1489-1517)",
            "optionA": "  I only ",
            "optionB": "  II only ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKabir is widely believed to have become the first disciple of the Bhakti poet-saint Swami Ramananda in Varanasi, known for devotional Vaishnavism with a strong bent to monist Advaita philosophy teaching that God was inside every person, everything. ",
            "keyString": "742234s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Bhakti cult spread in Maharashtra with the teaching of",
            "optionA": "  Sant Tukaram ",
            "optionB": "  Sant Jnanesvar ",
            "optionC": "  Samarth Guru Ramdas ",
            "optionD": "  Chaitanya Mahaprabhu ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSant Tukaram(c.1608 \u2013 c.1650), also Shri Tukaram, and colloquially referred to as \"Tuka\", was a seventeenth century Marathi poet Sant of India, related to the Bhakti movement of Maharashtra. Tukaram was a devotee of Vitthal (a form of Lord Krishna), the supreme God in Vaishnavism.",
            "keyString": "742268s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the Bhakti Saint Ramanuja?\nI.\u00a0He preached Vishishtadvaita.\nII.\u00a0He said that the 'God is Sagunabrahman'",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhakti Saint Ramanuja preached Vishishtadvaita. He said that the 'God is Saguna Brahman'. ",
            "keyString": "742298s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Bhakti saint believes that through love and devotion, song and dance, a devotee can feel the presence of God?",
            "optionA": "  Gnanadev ",
            "optionB": "  Chaitanya ",
            "optionC": "  Namadeva ",
            "optionD": "  Ekanatha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe greatest saint of the Bhakti movement was Shri Chaitanya, popularly known as Gouranga Mahaprabhu. He was born in 1486 A.D. at Navadweep in West Bengal in a Brahmin family. His childhood name was Nimai or Biswambhar Mishra. He was a promising student and mastered all branches of Sanskrit learning. After formal education he married Lakshmi Devi. But gradually he developed a sense of detachment towards worldly affairs. ",
            "keyString": "805376s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the Bhakti Saint Chaitanya?\nI.\u00a0He popularised the Krishna Cult in Bengal.\nII.\u00a0He believes that through love and devotion, song and dance, a devotee can feel the presence of God?",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChaitanya is said to have travelled all over India in spreading the Krishna Cult. He spent most of his time in Puri, Orissa on the feet of Lord Jagannath. He believes that through love and devotion, song and dance, a devotee can feel the presence of God. ",
            "keyString": "805691s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the disciple of Vallabhacharya?",
            "optionA": "  Tulsidas ",
            "optionB": "  Surdas ",
            "optionC": "  Tukaram ",
            "optionD": "  Ramanuja ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSurdas was the disciple of Vallabhacharya and he popularized Krishna cult in north India. ",
            "keyString": "805744s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Bhakti Reformers influenced by the preaching of Sufi teachers?",
            "optionA": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionB": "  Kabir ",
            "optionC": "  Nanak ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhakti Reformers influenced by the preaching of Sufi teachers were Ramananda, Kabir, Nanak. ",
            "keyString": "805764s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was the first Bhakti saint to use Hindi for the propagation of his message?",
            "optionA": "  Dadu ",
            "optionB": "  Kabir ",
            "optionC": "  Ramananda ",
            "optionD": "  Tulsidas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamananda was the first Bhakti saint to use Hindi for the propagation of his message. He was known for communicating in vernacular Hindi, and accepting disciples of all castes. ",
            "keyString": "805778s59m35h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}